Guide to the John C. Wilson Theater Collection on Noel Coward
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John C. Wilson Theater Collection on Noel Coward
1931-1955
GEN MSS 608
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(5 boxes)
Collection, including playscripts, production files, and printed materials, documenting the professional collaboration between American theater producer and director John C. Wilson and British playwright Noel Coward.
Wilson, John C., approximately 1899-1961
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc. on the Frederick W. Hilles Fund, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile papers in box 5 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
John C. Wilson (1899-1961)
Born in Trenton, New Jersey and educated at Phillips Academy and Yale University, John C. Wilson worked briefly for C. D. Barney & Co. on Wall Street before becoming a producer and director. From the early 1930s to mid 1950s Wilson served as Noel Coward's personal manager and, in 1934, with Coward, Lynn Fontanne, and Alfred Lunt, he established Transatlantic Productions, with exclusive production rights to Coward's plays in the United States. Wilson also served as co-director of the Westport Country Playhouse from the early 1940s to mid 1950s.
Scope and Contents
The collection, including playscripts, production files, and printed materials, documents the professional collaboration between American producer and director John C. Wilson and British playwright Noel Coward from 1931 to 1955. The collection features scripts for several plays, including Design for Living, Point Valaine, Time Remembered, Blithe Spirit, Present Laughter, Private Lives, Relative Values, Island Fling, and Quadrille. Accompanying production files include correspondence, cast lists, financial records, photographs, and other material. The correspondence, which includes fan mail to Coward, consists chiefly of letters between Wilson and others relating to production. Printed materials include clippings (reviews) and playbills, most for productions in the eastern United States.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by title.
American drama -- 20th Century; Dramatists, English -- 20th Century; English drama -- 20th Century; Theater -- Production and direction -- United States; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographic prints; Playbills; Playscripts; Dramatists; Coward, Noel, 1899-1973; Fontanne, Lynn, 1887-1983; Lunt, Alfred, 1892-1977; Wilson, John C., approximately 1899-1961; Transatlantic Productions; Westport Country Playhouse (Organization: Westport, Conn.)
- Blithe Spirit
  - Playscript, [ca. 1941-1942] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Production files, 1941-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Printed ephemera, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- "Call"
  - Production files, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Design for Living
  - Playscript, [1933] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Production files, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed ephemera, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Easy Virtue
  - Production files, 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- In Which We Serve
  - Production files, 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Printed ephemera, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Island Fling
  - Playscripts, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - Production files, 1949-1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Printed ephemera, 1949, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Point Valaine
  - Playscript, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Present Laughter
  - Playscripts, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
  - Printed ephemera, 1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Private Lives
  - Playscripts, [1949?] (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
  - Production files, 1947-1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Printed ephemera, 1948-1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Quadrille
  - Playscript, 1953 June 14 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Production files, 19[54]-1955 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Printed ephemera, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Relative Values
  - Playscripts, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
- Set to Music
  - Production files, 1938-1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Time Remembered
  - Playscript, [ca. 1940] (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Oversize, 1.67; (1 box)
  - Printed ephemera, 1939-1951 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 35-37)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Printed ephemera (Box 5, Folder 38-45)